Guide to the Alfred Geddes Papers MS 008
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Alfred Geddes Papers
1913-1959, (Bulk 1940-1950)
1940-1950
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Geddes, Alfred T.
MS 008
7.5 Linear Feet, 4 boxes and 1 OS Folder
Geddes was appointed Dean of Men at Danbury State Teacher's College in 1947 and served in that role until he retired in 1974. In 1939, he earned a Masters in education from Yale, and in 1955 received his Doctorate in Student Personnel from New York University. He joined the Army in the 1930s and served in the U.S. Army Air Corps during World War II. Geddes was a military history enthusiast and amassed a number of books on the subject. His papers contain personal materials from his career as an educator, soldier and military history collector.
Provenance
Donated to the Archives in 2002.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Alfred Geddes dedicated his life to education. He spent most of his life in Connecticut and became a fixture in the city of Danbury.
Alfred Thomas Geddes was born in Waterbury, Connecticut, on March 14, 1909, to William Geddes and Maryann Ryan Geddes. He was raised in New Haven, Connecticut, and lived there until he left to pursue his education. For most of his adult life, he lived in Brookfield, Connecticut.
In 1929, Geddes received his first college degree from Arnold College (in New Haven) where he earned his Bachelor of Science degree in physical education. He went on to receive his Bachelor of Science in education from Boston University in 1932. In 1939, he earned his Masters in education from Yale, and in 1955 he received his Doctorate in Student Personnel from New York University.
His teaching career began shortly after he was finished at Boston University. His first teaching job was at Oliver Perry High School in Providence, Rhode Island. He moved on to the Hamden School system in Hamden, Connecticut. He served as a teacher in physical education at both schools. Geddes also worked as an administrator at the Southbury Training School in Southbury, Connecticut. In 1937, Geddes began his tenure at Danbury State Teacher's College, now known as Western Connecticut State University. He served as the Dean of Men from 1947 until he retired in 1974.
During his tenure as Dean of Men, Geddes met his wife, Claire Trisch. She served as the Dean of Women from 1946 until she retired in 1975. They worked side by side as Deans for several years before they got married in 1958. The Geddes worked as deans of the college while Ruth A. Haas was the president. In fact, they were two of the original administrators hired by Haas. When all three retired (Alfred in 1974 and Claire and Ruth Haas in 1975), it marked the end of an era in the history of the university.
Geddes joined the Army Air Corps in the 1930s and served in World War II. He left the military with the rank of Lieutenant Colonel. Besides serving in the war, Geddes was fascinated with military history, and collected books about military history. Geddes was also a member of several clubs including the Rotary Club of Danbury and the Yale Club of New York City.
Alfred Geddes died in Danbury Hospital in Danbury, Connecticut, on April 15, 2001, at the age of 92.
Scope and Content Note
The collection documents his interest in education from his time as a student in the late 1920s up to his retirement from WCSU in 1974. The military materials contain materials from his days serving in the army in the 1930s and 1940s and books on military history that he collected.
In this collection are letters, photographs (one of which is framed) and a photo album, clippings, college papers a theses, maps, books, manuals, magazines, pamphlets, a phonograph record, newspapers, and a WWII era service man's hat.
There are several photographs of Geddes in uniform, including the framed photograph. Several old photographs of his family are found in the photo album. Most of the publications in this collection are army-training manuals, although there are some that are non-military related. The newspapers in this collection are issues Geddes kept from his time in the Pacific in World War II. They primarily came from the Philippines. Primarily Geddes' college papers and thesis date to his time at both Yale and NYU, although some appear to be done for him by students or done as part of a group effort. There are some yearbooks in this collection as well. Two yearbooks are from Arnold College (including his graduating year, 1929). There is also a 1975 Western Connecticut State College yearbook signed by Jim Dyer for Claire. There is also a copy of the book Henry Bernard: An Introduction, which was co-authored by Dr. Ralph Jenkins, the third president of this university.
The collection contains many newspaper and magazine articles that appear to have come from the Danbury News-Times, the New York Times, and the Boston Herald and magazines like Life. However, it is not known from which paper or magazine all the clippings originated as many articles were clipped without identifying information such as title or date. Included also are a set of U.S. military publications on tactics published during the Second World War and immediately after.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged topically.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Missing Title
Personal Papers
Printed material
Related Material
Truman Warner Papers.
Geddes Collection Monographs in Special Collections
Separated Material
The collection included a issues of newspapers and magazines; however, these items were removed from the collection due to their poor condition. These items include: The New York Times July 21, 1969, edition, the Boston Globe, News-Times, and Hartford Courant August 9, 1974, editions, and Life magazine November 23, 1936, November 18, 1946, and December 29, 1972 editions have been removed from this collection, but copies are available in the Haas Library.
Click here to view a list of books that were accessioned with this collecion. Books not in Special Collections are part of the Haas circulating collection.
Separated Materials
Civil War era photo album removed to the MS 060 Civil War Misc. Collection.
United States -- History -- World War, 1939-1945.; Universities and colleges -- Administration.; Clippings.; Publications.; Books; Correspondence.; Danbury (Conn.); Scrapbooks.; Waterbury (Conn.); Photographs.; Western Connecticut State University; Tisch, Claire.; Haas, Ruth A., 1903-1986.; United States. Army. Air Corps.; Danbury State Teachers College.; Geddes Family.
- Papers
  - Clippings (military)- various clippings dealing primarily w/World War II, obituaries, and magazine articles, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings (education)- included in these are clippings aboutcollegiate sports, 1932 Boston University Commencement, and Dr. Robert M. Hutchins, 1932-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings (personal)- local people and book reviews, 1945-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters and notes Geddes wrote while in the military, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Army Extension Course certificates and tests by Geddes, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Official letters Geddes received from the Army and War Department, 1932-1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Special Orders from the Army, 1934-1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous letters and manuals, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Various forms from the War Department, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Receipts of inventory purchases Geddes made, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Maps of the war, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Fighting Years book, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Manual, "Nuclear Weapons Employment," June 1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Manuals #1-, 1943-1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    General note
    - "Connecticut Men of the United States Army," Nov 1-3 & Nov 3-5, 1945, "Fallout Protection for Homes with Basements," May 1967, "Bulletin of the U.S. Army Medical Department," 1943
  - Manuals #2-, 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "Employment of the Cavalry," 1929, "Basic Field Manual Volume III: Basic Weapons," 1932, "Training Regulations: The Cavalry Rifle Squad," 1931, "Training Regulations: The Cavalry Rifle Platoon," 1931
  - Book- 6th Armored Division, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bureau of Engineering and Construction manual, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cavalry Operations manuals (1-30), ca.1929 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Military Training Regulations manuals, 1922-1931 (Box 1, Folder 19-23)
  - Military Reserve Officer magazine, February-October 1937 (Box 1, Folder 24-32)
  - Fragments from France, part 5 by Capt. Bruce Bairnsfather, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Fragments from France, part 6 by Capt. Bruce Bairnsfather, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - The Bystander's Fragments away from France, vol. 2, no. 8 by Capt. Bruce Bainsfather, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous, 1943-1992 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    -pamphlet "The World Federation System," sticker, "Still Serving: U.S. Army Retired," General Orders card, pamphlet "National Gettysburg Battlefield Tower," article "The World's Most Skilful Liar," (article about Joseph Goebbels), Fifth Air Force Christmas 1943 announcement, article "Under Fire with the Tenth U.S. Cavalry," article "Prejudice! Roadblock to Progress," article "The Last Horse Soldiers," two envelopes, jacket for the book Soldier
  - -New Haven Grays, 1816-1876, Lucke, Jerome B. (Box 1, Folder *)
  - -The Menace from Moresby: A Pictorial History of the 5th Air Force in World War II, compiled by Sinton, Russell L., n.d. (ca 1946), undated (Box 1, Folder *)
  - Personal photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Letters and postcards, 1938-1988 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Danbury State College "Class of 1960" program and photograph for Claire Geddes, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Illustration- "Danbury State Teacher's College", 1942 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Cutter, Richard, "Over and Out; Sam's Story", 1999 (Box 2, Folder 41-43)
  - Book of images of Danbury and surrounding towns, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Story of John F. Kennedy book, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Personal miscellaneous #1, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    -handbook "The Mass on the Day of Marriage,"1955, certificate for Geddes, March 1942, Fiftieth anniversary diploma for James Geddes from the Mercersburg Academy (Mercersburg, Pennsylvania), October 1967, Memorial Service announcement from Yale (James Geddes), June 10, 1973, St. Joseph's Church service announcements (James Geddes), July 27, 1975
  - Personal miscellaneous #2, 1934-1956 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    -cash receipt, May 31, 1939, flyer from The Dehner Company, Inc. w/ order form and price list, August 7, 1936, papers w/ Asian writing, Greenwich Library bookwagon schedule, 1958-1959, report on a young men from the "New Jersey State Home for Boys," 1934-1936, parade orders "Danbury's New Look Celebration," November 15, 1956, article "Writing Man, Fighting Man," business cards, "Katten and Sons" uniform price list, envelope
  - Letters dealing w/ education, 1929-1945 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Yale Thesis- "The Health Program in the ElementarySchools of Connecticut", 1939 (Box 2, Folder 49-50)
  - NYU Paper- "Introduction to Student Personnel Services in Colleges and Universities," (Dr. Cornehlsen, professor), December, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Outline for NYU thesis on Danbury State Teacher'sCollege- "A Study of the Personnel Services Program for Students in the Elementary Teacher Education Curriculum at Danbury State Teacher's College," May 14, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Papers from NYU by Geddes, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
    -"Testing and Student Personnel Work," (unknown date), "Organization and Administration Educational Guidance," (Dr. Cornehlsen, professor), January 1950, "In-Service Education for Faculty," (unknown date)
  - NYU Papers miscellaneous, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Danbury Elementary School source book, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - 1928 Yale Commencement book (two) (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Yale Club of New York City books, (1949-50, 1981) (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Danbury State Teacher's College and Danbury StateCollege program books, (1950-51, 1956-57, 1964) (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Boston University commencement 1932, Hamden HighSchool Program (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Teacher's Education Quarterly, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Lectures on Dr. Eliot's Five-Foot Shelf of Books, no. 8(education), 10 (drama), 11 (voyages & travel), and 12 (religion), 1913 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - CT Geology books w/ maps (see OS folder for maps), 1951-1954 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    -"Bedrock Geology of the Litchfield Quadrangle," 1951, "Geology of the New Preston Quadrangle," 1952, "Bedrock Geology of the Woodbury Quadrangle," 1954
  - New Jersey State Home for Boys 7th annual report, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - New College catalogues, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Education miscellaneous, 1928-1930 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    -Harvard University "Intramural Athletics," 1928-1929, B.U. "Athletic Regulations," 1929, Arnold College football schedule, 1928-1929, College baseball schedule, 1930, Boston University Athletic Council flyer, commencement card Sheffield Scientific School
  - Serviceman's hat, undated (Box OS 1, Item 17)
- Printed Materials and Miscellanea
  - Miscellaneous
    - -Henry Barnard: An Introduction, Jenkins, Ralph Ph. D. and Gertrude Warner, 1937 (Box 2, Item 1)
    - -Yale Club of New York City, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Item 2)
    - -University Club, 1961 (Box 2, Item 3)
    - -History of the Class of 1928: Sheffield Scientific School (Box 2, Item 4)
    - -Arnold College yearbooks, 1927-1929 (Box 2, Item 5)
    - -Western Connecticut State College Yearbook,1975 (signed by Jim Dyer for Claire) (Box 2, Item 6)
    - -NYU Thesis "A Study of the Personnel Services Program for the Students in the Elementary Teacher Education Curriculum at Danbury State Teacher's College", 1955 (Box 2, Item 7)
    - -Yale Thesis "An Integration of the Extra School Agencies of a Community with the School Program", 1936 (Box 2, Item 8)
    - -Other Thesis "Guidance at the Secondary School Level," (Dr. Clyde Hill, professor), undated (Box 2, Item 9)
    - Record- Dec 7, 1941, undated (Box OS 1, Item 1)
    - Photo album, 1850s-1880s (Box OS 1, Item 2)
      General
      This album is of unknown provenance. It appears to be a family album from around the Civil War. Some names include: Porth, Stoll, and Freune. Subjects were photographed in New Haven, New York, and San Francisco.
    - Framed photograph of Geddes in uniform, undated (Box OS 1, Item 3)
    - Two photographs of Geddes regiment, undated (Box OS 1, Item 4)
    - Panoramic Photograph of (Commercial High School) CHS, 1926 class (Folder OS 2)
      Formerly located on Tower Parkway in New Haven, CT; area now part of Yale University.
    - "The World At War" map, February 1943 (map is seen in framed photograph) (Box OS 1, Item 6)
    - Sheet music: "2nd Regiment of Connecticut National Guard", undated (Box OS 1, Item 7)
    - Scrapbooks of space exploration and "Project Rescue", undated (Box OS 1, Item 8)
    - Newspaper: The Courier Mail (Brisbane), April 30, May 3,7-9, 19, June 12, 1945. (Box OS 1, Item 9)
    - Newspaper: The Sunday Mail (Brisbane), April 29, 1945 (Box OS 1, Item 10)
    - Philippine Press, May 8, 1945, Free Philippines, March15, April 25, 1945, Victory News, March 27, 1945, Manila Chronicle, April 21, 1945, Manila Daily Mail, May 10, 1945 (Box OS 1, Item 11)
    - The Tribune, (Manila, Philippines), February 8; March 29; April 5, 26, 28; June 7, 17, 1944. (Box OS 1, Item 12)
    - Sunday Tribune, (Manila, Philippines), March 12;September 19, 26; October 31; November 14, 1944 (Box OS 1, Item 13)
    - Daily Pacifican, August 11-12, 25-26, 29-31, September 1,9, 12, 18, 23, 1945 (Box OS 1, Item 14)
    - The Commercial News, (Commercial High School, New Haven, CT), September 28, 1944 (Box OS 1, Item 15)
    - Maps from CT Geology books, undated (Box OS 1, Item 16)
  - Military publications
    - Supplemental Material on the First World War, Jul 1939 (Box 3, Item 1)
    - The Campaign in Poland 1939, Jul 1942 (Box 3, Item 2)
    - The Campaign in the West 1940, Jul 1942 (Box 3, Item 3)
    - Operations of the Russian Front Part 1: 22 June 1941 to November 1942, Feb 1943 (Box 3, Item 4)
    - Operations of the Russian Front Part 2: November, 1942 - December, 1943, Feb 1944 (Box 3, Item 5)
    - Great Captains Before Napoleon, 1945 (Box 3, Item 6)
    - Jomini, Clausewitz and Schlieffen, 1945 (Box 3, Item 7)
    - Campaign Summaries Part 1: To Include the First World War, 1945 (Box 3, Item 8)
    - Operations of the Russian Front Part 3: January - December 1944, Mar 1945 (Box 3, Item 9)
    - The Invasion of Western Europe Part 1: 6 June to 31 December 1944, Dec 1945 (Box 3, Item 10)
    - Notes on Combat Maneuvers, 1946 (Box 3, Item 11)
    - Campaign Summaries Part 2: World War II, 1946 (Box 3, Item 12)
    - The Invasion of Western Europe Part 2: January to May 1945, Mar 1946 (Box 3, Item 13)
    - German Defense Tactics Against Russian Break-Throughs, No. 20-233 (classified), Oct 1951 (Box 3, Item 14)